南宋 武當觀
1262年
本字幕由ZiMuZu原創翻譯
最新下載請登錄www.ZiMuZu.tv
翻譯   兮之  圈圈
李金寶
Li Jinbao.
時間軸  想念Gallifrey的Wholock
蒙古人
Mongols.
他們已經摧毀了北峰的道觀
They have already destroyed the temple at North Peak.
校對  圈圈
-道姑在哪裏  -在東邊道觀裏
- Where are the nuns? - In the cloisters. East.
後期  寶寶
記住我們的誓言  我們會血戰到底
Remember the oath. We fight to the end.
得道之人  生死一線
Life and death are one thread.
總監  圈圈
我會守護那些書卷
I will guard the scrolls.
打開微信   掃瞄左側二維碼
或搜索公眾號:    ustvboom
瞭解最新影視字幕發佈信息
李金寶
Li Jinbao!
別殺他
Do not kill him.
大汗要見他
The Khan will want this one.
馬克波羅
百眼特輯
到底是什麼樣的道士這麼厲害
What kind of monk is able to kill,
能一人斬殺25名蒙古士兵呢
by himself, 25 Mongol soldiers?
這是你們道觀裏的巫術嗎
Is it a form of dark magic practiced at your temple?
你永遠無從得知
You shall never know, shall you?
你剛說什麼
What did you just say, monk?
你剛摧毀了一座道觀
You destroyed a temple
而那座道觀內珍藏著無數古代卷軸
and all of the ancient scrolls
卷軸內就有你想知道的問題的答案
that contained the answers you seek.
你們在庇護南宋人  而他們是我的敵人
You monks were offering shelter to my enemies in South China.
無論什麼地方都不能蔑視可汗的命令
No place defies the Khan.
我再問你一次
I will ask you again.
如果你還是不說  那你的舌頭就不必留下了
If you hold your tongue, I will take your tongue.
你們藏匿在深山道觀中的武藝到底是什麼
What is this fighting art kept secret in a mountain temple?
和平之術
The art of peace.
你折斷了精銳士兵的脖子
You break the necks of trained soldiers,
割開他們的喉嚨  將他們像野豬一樣開膛破肚
cut their throats, gut them like wild pigs,
你說這是和平
and you call it peace?
你毀了一座道觀  還稱其為命運使然呢
You destroy a temple and call it destiny?
若是先王  絕不會饒恕你
Kings of the past would not have shown you grace.
而我  當我攻打一座城池時
Me, when I make war on a city,
裏面的手藝人我不會趕盡殺絕
I allow the craftsmen to live.
我徵召他們  如此他們就得以活命
I conscript them into service... and they live.
看這裏
Here.
你要把這種神秘的中原武藝告訴我的軍政大臣
You will reveal these Chinese secrets to my war ministers.
教你們中原武藝  好讓你們用來攻擊中原人嗎
Reveal Chinese secrets... to fight the Chinese.
證明你自己有用  你才能活下來
Prove yourself useful, you can live.
不服從我的命令
Defy my laws...
你的死法會比那些和卷軸一起死去的道士們
you'll die a death far worse than that suffered by the monks
可怕得多
who perished with your scrolls.
你覺得我的命令很可笑是嗎
Oh, you find humor in my decree?
世上只有一個頂級劊子手
There is only one Supreme Executioner.
其他那些妄圖取代他的人
And those who try to take his place
就好比班門弄斧
are like children trying to carve wood as a master carpenter.
大多只會傷了自己的手
Most will injure their own hands.
你不怕死嗎
You do not fear death?
我不汲汲於活命
I do not cling to life.
這兩者是有區別的
There is a difference.
帶他下去
Remove him.
這名摔跤手名為黑原野豬
This wrestler is named Black Steppe Boar.
是我們在賽西亞俘虜的一名囚犯
A prisoner captured in Scythia.
你知道他為什麼會叫野豬嗎
Do you know why he is named after the boar?
因為他的長相很奇特
His resemblance is extraordinary.
他被稱作野豬
He is called Boar
是因為他多次赤手空拳屠殺他人
because he has killed such without a weapon many times.
野豬會衝上來  抓住你
Boar will advance. He will seize you.
你就會展示出你是如何脫出他的掌控的
You will demonstrate how to break the grasp.
你要蒙上我的眼睛嗎
You cover my eyes?
這公平嗎
Is that just?
大汗想知道你蒙眼之下是如何作戰的
The Great Khan wants a report on how you fight blindfolded.
他真是任性妄為 愚蠢之極
He is a most capricious fool.
你要是夠膽子的話  就把我的原話傳達給他
And if you were not cowards, you would tell him the same.
閉嘴  道士
Quiet, monk!
你剛才殺死的將軍是速不台的兒子
The general you killed was the son of Subutai.
你聽過這個名字嗎  道士
Do you know that name, monk?
沒有
I do not.
他是成吉思汗手下第一悍將
Greatest military commander ever to serve Genghis Khan.
你殺死了他的兒子
You slayed his son.
這是重罪
This is a crime beyond crimes.
但是
Yet...
你說你不汲汲於活命
you do not cling to life, as you say.
最新美劇下載
www.ZiMuZu.tv
死亡並無意義
Death means nothing.
那可汗該怎麼辦呢
What is a Khan to do?
曾經有個商人送了我一隻小亞亞美尼亞的白鶴
A merchant once gifted me a white crane from Lesser Armenia...
那是一種十分稀罕的水鳥
a water bird that was most uncommon...
因為它一生下來就全身漆黑
because it had been born all black.
一隻黑色的白鶴
Black white crane.
我知道這是一種吉兆
I knew it was an auspicious
它能給我帶來好運  但是
being that would bring me fortune, but...
那只黑色的白鶴不願待在我的湖泊裏
that black white crane refused to stay on my lake.
它總是妄圖飛走
Always, it would fly away.
它的本性在召喚它
Just its natural calling, you see.
然後
So...
為了讓它給我帶來好運
I served him and my fortune...
我斷了它一隻翅膀
by cutting one wing.
眾王之王
"By law of the Grand Khan,
大汗有旨
Lord of Lords..."
你覺得我為什麼讓你蒙眼戰鬥
Why do you think I had you fight blindfolded?
因為我任性妄為 愚蠢之極嗎
Because I'm a capricious fool?
還是想看看你在黑暗中
Or to see if you are capable
能不能使出你那些道教秘術呢
of your Taoist secrets and skills while in the dark?
欽此
"So be it."
我一看到你就知道
Because I knew the moment you were presented,
你不是那種順從的畫家
you would not be like the obedient painter...
聽天由命的占星家  有酒萬事足的詩人
the resigned astrologer, the noble poet contented with wine.
你不會原意順從蒙古帝國
You would refuse to serve the Mongol Empire.
直到今日
To this day...
那只黑色的白鶴還在我的湖上
that black white crane remains on my lake.
它是我的
He is mine...
心愛之物
and he is beloved.
你現在準備好...
Are you now ready...
教授我的軍政大臣了嗎
to teach my Ministers of Warfare?
給道士上茶
Tea for the monk.
我不是和尚  不要給我茶
Do not confuse me with one of your holy Buddhists.
給我酒
Wine.
你之前是因殺害速不台的兒子受罰
You were punished for killing the son of Subutai.
不要忘記這點
Never forget that.
我不會忘的
I shall not.
武當派的道士們窮盡一生
The monks of Wudang spend their lives
想達到真正的空性
trying to achieve true emptiness.
聖人只有克服自我
For only when the sage can overcome the self
才能領悟道的真意
does he enter into the Tao.
這是眾謎之外的黑暗之謎
That is a dark mystery beyond all mysteries,
是你贈給我的禮物
and a gift you gave to me.
我雖瞎
Blind?
但卻能以百眼看世界
I now see the world with one hundred eyes.
再給他倒酒
Give him more wine.
我剛抓住了你的馬
I've just captured your horse.
我知道
I know.
我告訴你
Then know this.
武當山上
There are four Taoist temples
還有四座道觀
still standing in the Wudang Mountains.
我的人半月後會到那裏把它們都燒成灰
My men will go there in a fortnight and burn them to the ground.
只需我一聲令下
At my single command,
你信仰的宗教就會從世界上消失
your religion can be wiped off the face of this earth.
或者  它可以繼續存在下去
Or it can live...
發展
grow...
壯大
thrive...
前提是你向我證明它的價值
if you prove its value to me.
通過訓練你的大臣嗎
By training your ministers?
還有一個人
And someone else.
你一定就是王子了吧
You must be the prince.
我叫阿爾泰
I am called Altai.
你來這裏做什麼
Why are you here?
上課
Lessons.
你想通過這些...課程
And what do you intend to teach me
讓我學到什麼
in these... lessons?
我想讓你知道  即使是大汗的兒子
I'm here to teach you that even the son of a royal khan
也知謙恭  知學習
is capable of humility and learning.
那就拿起掃帚掃地  阿爾泰
Then take the broom, Altai, and sweep my floor.
回答得好  如果你相信的話
Good answer. If only you believed it.
你是世界大花園裏的一株小草
You are a little nomad weed in the garden of the world.
他們想讓你長成參天大樹
They wish you to grow into a flowering tree.
這棵樹上最重要的部分是什麼
What is the most important part of such a tree?
樹枝  還有樹上的花
The many branches and the flowering.
我指的是遺產
I speak of legacy.
謝謝你跟我解釋你晦澀的比喻
Thank you for untangling your elusive metaphor.
我們從根基開始練起
We begin with roots.
我能問一個問題嗎
May I ask a question?
說
Do.
如果你想在牆上寫字
If you wish calligraphy on your wall,
為什麼不找個眼不瞎的書法家來
why not summon a painter who can see?
你沒看到我寫的是什麼嗎
Can you not read the character I made?
它代表的是火
It is a symbol for fire.
有何異常
Then what is wrong?
-倒置了  -沒錯
- It's upside down. - Precisely.
這在功夫世界中代表的是耐心  自控
This is the kung fu character for patience, control.
你要永遠記住
Remember this in the future, always,
絕不讓憤怒打敗你
"Never give way to anger."
師父
Sifu?
我沒教過你要保持安靜嗎
Have I not trained you into exhausted silence yet?
今天的課上完了  王子殿下
Today's lesson is done, My Radiant Highness.
我知道你看不到  但是...
You cannot see it, I know. But...
我向你保證  這是由一位
I assure you it has been overseen
偉大的漢族建築師
by a great Chinese architect...
用最珍貴的木材和皮草建起來的...
made from the most precious of woods and hides, and--
大膽
imbecile.
有人把漢字"火"倒寫在這裏了
Someone has painted the character of fire upside down.
是我寫的
I did.
值此新春佳節之際
On this day of the New Year...
我將此處命名為四寶之廳
I ordain this place the Hall of the Fourth Treasure.
給你賜名百眼
I name you Hundred Eyes...
軍事大臣
...Minister of Martial Affairs.
所以
And so...
我請你這位武當道士
I ask of you, as a Wudang priest,
給我兒子取一個漢族名字
give my son his Chinese name.
從古至今
There have been 500 over time
已有500多位皇帝統治過中國
who have held the name Emperor of All China,
他們自稱為天子
Son of Heaven.
雖憑血緣繼承王位
Ordained by blood,
但其實與統治世界上
there are those who would have been
最偉大的帝國相比
better suited to harvest cow dung
有的人可能更適合去撿牛糞
than to rule the greatest empire on earth.
有人就如銀子
There are those who were as silver,
雖不是堅硬無比  但值得鑄幣
a lesser metal, but worthy of coinage.
還有人...
And then there are those...
如冰冷的石頭
like cold stone,
全靠蠻力和憤怒
who force their strength and fury
通過威嚇他人贏得皇位
and win the title by fear and intimidation.
血緣無關緊要
Blood is nothing.
想成為聖賢  靠的是心靈和精神
Heart and spirit make the sage.
因此
And by this...
我給他取名為真金
I give this boy the name Jingim.
"真正的金子"
"True gold."
那就這樣吧
So be it.
他以後就用這個名字了
He will walk out of here with this name,
這個名字將伴隨他到達聖賢可見的明天
and carry it as his own into a tomorrow only the oracles can see.
至於你  道士
As for you, priest...
這座道觀歸你了
this temple is yours.